Finding aid for the Layne Nielson papers LSC.2236
UCLA Library Special Collections
Layne Nielson papers
1938-2002
1960-2002
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nielson, Layne
LSC.2236
16.2 linear feet (14 boxes, 1 carton, 6 flat boxes, and 8 oversize flat boxes)
6 video recordings (6 unprocessed VHS tapes)
1 sound recordings (1 unprocessed 12 inch 45 rpm record)
6 linear feet (3 unprocessed outfits)
Layne Nielson is a fashion and graphic designer who designed fashion accessories and stationery for Rudi Gernreich and for his own label. The collection includes fashion samples and accessories, as well as sketches, publicity, stationery, examples of Nielson's design work in advertising, photographs, publications, and documentation of exhibitions.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Layne Nielson, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9982209303606533
Biographical History
Designer Layne Nielson is known for his work designing fashion accessories and stationery for Rudi Gernreich. Nielson's work reflects a wide range of design, including: graphics, product design, textiles, exhibition design, and interior design.
Nielson was born in Monroe, Utah on March 3, 1938. As a college student, Nielson moved to Los Angeles in 1958 and worked in the UCLA Library, where he befriended Paul Lenk, a cousin of Gernreich's. Lenk introduced Nielson to Gernreich, who offered him work if Nielson would learn to design hats. This began a long relationship between Nielson and Gernreich. Nielson worked both as a freelance designer and as an Assistant Designer to Gernreich at various times between 1959-1985. The foremost expert on Gernreich, Nielson lectures on Gernreich, has extensive involvement with exhibitions on Gernreich, and began a biography of Gernreich in 1996.
Nielson's other commercial design work includes stationery design, advertising, and other graphic design. Nielson designed variously as Layne Nielson Design Company, Nielson Design Company, and Dynasty Collection. He also worked for Hoffman California Woolens, Wilson/Levin/Kirk, Western Costume Company, Max Factor and Company, Redken laboratories, EGR Travel, and others, and opened the Layne Nielson/ Selective Eye art gallery.
Source: Nielson's Curriculum Vitae and his autobiographical narrative accounts, Box 26, Folder 1, Layne Nielson papers (Collection 2236). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material related to the career of designer Layne Nielson. Included are fashion design samples and accessories, sketches, correspondence, publicity, photographs, assorted graphic designs samples, exhibition ephemera, photographs, and publications. Additionally, there is a small amount of material documenting Nielson's childhood. Some boxes may contain autobiographical narratives written by Nielson to provide context to items in the collection. The materials date from 1938 to 2002.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Fashion accessories, design, and show production, 1960-2002
Series 2: Graphic design, 1960-1999
Series 3: Photographs, 1939-1990
Series 4: Juvenilia and memorabilia, 1938-1999
Related Material
Rudi Gernreich papers (Collection 1702). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Layne Nielson collection on George Hoyningen-Huene (Collection 2232). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Designers -- California -- Archives; Nielson, Layne; Nielson, Layne -- Archives
- Series 1: Fashion accessories, design, and show production, 1960-2002
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
  Scope and Content
  Fashion accessories, design and show production includes fashion and accessories designed by Nielson, as well as related publicity. Also included are exhibition ephemera and correspondence, and writings and publications by Nielson that relate to his career in fashion design. Additionally, this series includes sketches, videos, advertisements, correspondence, ephemera, and clippings related to costumes designed by Nielson, and shows produced or directed by Nielson.
  - Collocation of box inventories and narrative accounts, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Fashion press clippings, Max Factor design, and exhibition photographs, circa 1960-1969, 1974, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    Includes a design for Max Factor that was never produced, fashion press clippings with design credits, and Metropolitan Museum of Art Apropos Apron exhibition photographs.
  - Editorial publicity, The Rudi Gernreich Book, and Los Angeles Chamber Ballet Cocktails with Joey materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 2-10)
    Includes Rizzoli and Taschen editions of The Rudi Gernreich Book and Nielson's response to it as well as Rudi Gernreich: A Retrospective with inset photographs. Also includes editorial publicity, correspondence, and clippings along with Los Angeles Chamber ballet Cocktails with Joey design notes, a list of scenes, and transparencies.
  - Accessories portfolio, exhibition photographs, and publications, 1964-1988 (Box 5)
    Includes a portfolio of fashion accessories for Rudi Gernreich, design photographs for Rudi Gernreich: A Tribute exhibition at Otis/Parsons, and publications with design credits.
  - Max Factor Futuro promotion scrapbook, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    Scrapbook includes clippings, correspondence, photographs, and press kits. Also includes family correspondence from the Futuro tours and Playboy's Creative Menswear International Designer Collection 1974 catalog featuring Gernreich's Futuro designs.
  - Promotion files and scrapbook, 1975-1976, 1986 (Box 9)
    Includes files for Nielson's work for Max Factor on An Echo of Deco, for Redken Laboratories, and for May Company at Saluting the California Woman. Files include clippings, correspondence, programs, and press kits.
  - Correspondence, clippings, and documentation related to the Rudi Gernreich collection at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, undated (Box 10)
  - Cocktails with Joey materials and Rudi Gernreich exhibition clipping, 1999, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
    Includes Cocktails with Joey press clippings, correspondence, and working drawings. Also includes an article by Beth Moore on a Rudi Gernreich exhibition.
  - Publications, Dynasty Collection materials, and museum exhibition materials, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
    Includes publications with design credits, fashion history books, Dynasty Collection lingerie venture records, fashion accessories, and museum photographs. Also includes museum exhibition ephemera, clippings, programs, and photographs.
  - Editorial publicity, 1960-1969 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Wool knit and leather knapsack, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Wool knit sweaters, 1967 (Box 15)
    Two sweaters designed for Harmon Knitwear but not produced.
  - White Breton hat for Carol Channing, 1968 (Box 16)
  - Black velour toque, 1967 (Box 17)
  - Dance costume sketches, 1999-2000 (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    Includes sketches for costumes for Los Angeles Chamber Ballet Cocktails with Joey and Ririe/Woodbury Dance Company Let's Dance.
  - Fashion publicity in periodicals, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 1-7)
  - Invitation, interview, and promotional videos, 1967, 1998, 2000; 6 video recordings (6 unprocessed VHS tapes) (Box 22)
    Includes a boxed invitation designed by Nielson to celebrate Gernreich's receipt of the Coty Hall of Fame Award, a VHS of an interview with Nielson to promote a Gernreich exhibition, and five VHS tapes promoting Cocktails with Joey.
  - Lecture announcements, essays by Nielson, and a monograph, 2001-2002 (Box 23, Folder 3-4, 9)
    Included among the essays is an excerpt on Marian Anderson from Nielson's Gernreich biography.
  - Publications, 1969, 2000-2001 (Box 24, Folder 1-5)
    Two Fashion Will Go Out of Fashion exhibition catalogs and one copy of Crackers featuring Nielson accessories.
  - Labels, clippings, publications, and negatives, 1965, 1967, undated (Box 25, Folder 3, 4, 9)
    Includes Rudi Gernreich labels, photo transparencies by Christa Zinner, and clippings related to Nielson's suit for Harmon Knitwear. Publications include a Klimt exhibition catalog.
  - Bistro table linen designed for Rudi Gernreich and Barth & Dreyfus, 1977 (Box 27)
    Includes table linen and merchandise tags.
  - Jewelry and Austrian peasant calendar, 1964-1968 (Box 28)
    Includes metal bracelets and a ring from Berger's Jewelry Supply, a wired chiffon ear clip, and an Austrian peasant calendar that inspired a scarf collection.
  - Silk scarves, 1965-1968 (Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32)
    21 silk scarves from seven Gernreich scarf collections. Box 28 includes two oblong Austrian peasant calendar scarves and two oblong military insignia scarves. Box 29 includes five square Klimt-inspired scarves. Box 30 includes one typography scarf, one military-inspired scarf, and two square traffic sign scarves. Box 31 includes four square Klimt-inspired scarves. Box 32 includes four Austrian peasant calendar scarves.
- Series 2: Graphic design, 1960-1999
  Graphic design includes invitations, letterheads, and Christmas cards from Nielson's work designing stationery. Also included are sketches, prints, clippings, and publications from Nielson's work in advertising.
  - Invitations, Christmas cards, and interior designs, 1962-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    Includes Atrium Court Gala designs, invitations, and party favors; interior designs for General Lee's Restaurant; personal Christmas cards; and Rudi Gernreich Christmas card designs.
  - Personal promotional designs and advertising designs., circa 1960-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    Includes personal promotional designs; packaging designs for Exquisite Form Industries, New York; Layne Nielson/Selective Eye Gallery mailing announcements and advertisements for exhibition openings; illustrations and advertising designs for G. Michael Hennessy Designer Furs, Beverly Hills and Ohrbach's Fur Salon, Los Angeles; and stationery, business cards, and announcements designs.
  - Advertisements, publications, and invitations., 1971-1972, 1984-1989, 1993-1994; 1 sound recordings (1 unprocessed 12 inch 45 rpm record) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    Contains advertising designs with Sunset Post Ads and Steffler and Associates, including designs for General Foods Corporation, Quaker Oats, and Hanna-Barbera; a record sleeve for Longhorn Records; and press preview books for California Mart.
  - Panasonic special event invitations, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Invitations and publications, 1985-1986, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    Includes Langue et Langage French textbook, Lambda Legal invitations and UCLA brochures, Cannon Films publications, and the Los Angeles Business Journal.
  - Corporate identification design, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    Corporate identification design for Brighton Design Company and graphic design for Arena Video.
  - Book cover design, advertisements, and furniture designs, 1965, 1985, 1990 (Box 10)
    Includes a mock-up for a rejected cover design for Rudi Gernreich: A Retrospective, advertisements for Nielson Design Company, and furniture designs.
  - Atrium Court Gala poster and program, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Designs never produced, Atrium Court Gala materials, and stationery samples, 1960-1999 (Box 13, Folder 5-9)
    Includes designs never produced; samples from Fabriano and Crane, including Nielson designs used to advertise the quality of Crane products; and Atrium Court Gala invitations, photographs, and clippings.
  - Letterheads, cards, and invitations, undated (Box 18, Folder 13-17)
  - Letterhead designs, stationery, and engraving trade publications, 1987-1996 (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
  - Hand-lettered typestyle, cards, and book, 1964, 1986, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 5-8)
    Includes hand-lettered typestyle for Gernreich, title treatments, personal Christmas cards, and a book that Nielson designed and published.
  - Publicity, photographs and sketches, and cards, 1973, 1985, undated (Box 24, Folder 6, 9, 10)
    Includes publicity for the Selective Eye Art Gallery, Atrium Court Gala photographs and sketches, and Gernreich Christmas cards.
  - Selective Eye Art Gallery documents, cards, and company identification, 1970-1979 (Box 25, Folder 5-8, 10)
    Includes Selective Eye Art Gallery photographs, sales documents, and editorial publicity; an article on Gernreich's Christmas cards; and Paul R. Davies and RVG company identification.
- Series 3: Photographs, 1939-1990
  Photographs include portraits of Nielson by George Hoyningen-Huene, Mel Fellini, Paul R. Davis, and others. This series includes photographs from Nielson's world travels, including those from his 1979 trip to China, and photographs of friends and family.
  - Photographs of China and Haiti and for proposed advertisements, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, transparencies, and negatives of Haiti, Peru, Guatemala, undated (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
    Also includes two magazines in which Nielson's photographs appear.
  - Travel photographs and negatives and photographs of people, 1968-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    Photographs of China, Thailand, England and Wales, New York, and San Juan. Photographs of people include Mary Guggenheim, Jim Jones, Pauline Annon, Eleanor Bedell, Lori McCormack, Abelin Jolicoeur, Alvin Meldrum, Michael Crowder, and David Graham.
  - Photographs and negatives by Mel Fellini, 1965, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Also includes a photograph of Nielson at Joshua Tree National Park.
  - Photographs of Nielson and family photographs, 1939-1990 (Box 18, Folder 5-12)
    Photographs include portraits of Nielson by Susan Swanezy, Paul R. Davies, and George Hoyningen-Huene. They also include a photograph of Nielson with Yolanda Penteado, family photographs, photographs with friends, and negatives.
- Series 4: Juvenilia and memorabilia, 1938-1999
  Juvenilia and memorabilia includes childhood art, school yearbooks and a scrapbook, passports, military uniform items, and military papers.
  - Childhood art and school records, 1944-1950 (Box 11, Folder 3, Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Military documents, birth certificate, passports, and a caricature, 1938, 1960-1999. (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
    Includes passports, a copy of Nielson's birth certificate, and a caricature Nielson believes to be the work of William Hamilton. Military documents include uniform patches and pins, photographs, papers, and clippings.
  - Scrapbook, early artwork, and school records, 1943-1963 (Box 20, Folder 5-7)
    Includes a scrapbook of high school activities, early artwork, and school records, including a high school diploma.
  - Family correspondence, undated (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Yearbooks and postcards from China, 1953-1958, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 1-2, Box 26, Folder 2-3, Box 24, Folder 7, 8, 11)
    Postcards may be found in Box 24. Nielson designed the 1956 yearbook.